<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breefe declaration of that which is happened aswell within as without Oastend sithence the vij. of Ianuarie 1602 As also when the enemy did giue foure, fiue, or more assaults vpon the same towne. Also the names of the commaunders of those which haue made these assaults vpon the towne of Oastend, and the names of the said conductors which haue been slaine.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113597</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848830</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848830</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13946</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08571)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13946)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1212:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breefe declaration of that which is happened aswell within as without Oastend sithence the vij. of Ianuarie 1602 As also when the enemy did giue foure, fiue, or more assaults vpon the same towne. Also the names of the commaunders of those which haue made these assaults vpon the towne of Oastend, and the names of the said conductors which haue been slaine.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Schilders. 1602. At London printed for Mathew Law,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Middleborrow :</pubPlace>
                  <date>(1602.)</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ostend (Belgium) --  History --  Siege, 1601-1604 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13946:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13946:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Breefe Declaration Of that which is happened aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well within as without <hi>Oastend</hi> ſithence the vij. of Ianuarie 1602. As alſo when the Enemy did giue Foure, Fiue, or more Aſſaults vpon the ſame Towne. Alſo <hi>The names of the Commaunders of thoſe which haue made theſe Aſsaults</hi> vpon the towne of <hi>Oaſtend,</hi> and the names of the ſaid Conductors which haue been ſlaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Middleborrow</hi> Printed by Richard Schilders. 1602.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON Printed for Mathew Law.</hi> (1602.)</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13946:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13946:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A breefe declaration of that <hi>which is paſsed aſwell within, as</hi> without the towne of <hi>Oaſtend. &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the Arch-duke <hi>Albertus</hi> with his forces, about Seauen moneths paſte being came before the towne of <hi>Oaſtend,</hi> hath cauſed the ſame preſently to be battered, and hath cauſed the ſame to bee continued during this Beſieging without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuance: ſo that from the beginning of this ſiege vntill the vij. of Ianuarie <hi>1602.</hi> vpon the Towne hath béen ſhot One Hundreth Six and Thirty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Cannon ſhot. And perceauing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> after theſe many thouſand ſhot which he hath ſhot vpon the Towne, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame hath nothing preuayled as he had well hoped: He hath on the vij. of this moneth of Ianuarie <hi>1602</hi> from the morning betimes till the after-noone, ſhotte more then Thirtéene Hundreth ſhotte. After which, on the ſaid day he hath done ſeuerall Aſſaults aſwell vppon the towne of <hi>Oaſtend,</hi> as the other Forts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ioyning, not doubting but he ſhould haue forced the towne by reaſon of the want of Souldiers within it, as he thought, but God hath otherwiſe prouided.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13946:3"/>
               <head>The ſucceſſe of the <hi>vij.</hi> day.</head>
               <p>ON the Seauenth day of Ianuarie aforeſaid af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ſtile, the Spaniards with the Italian alloted vnto them, either of them vnder their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals and Commaunders came marching towards the Towne of <hi>Oaſtend</hi> vnder the conduct as followeth.</p>
               <p>The Earle of <hi>Truſtie</hi> or <hi>Triúùlſie</hi> Italian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder of Two Thouſand Italians, fell vppon the <hi>Santhill</hi> but was verie valiantly beaten thereof.</p>
               <p>The Earle of <hi>Bucquoy</hi> chéefe of Two Thouſand men made aſſally vpon the Eaſt Rauelin, but as the water was flowen too high, he was conſtrained to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the ſame, and fell vppon the halfe Moone ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Geule,</hi> from whence hee was manfully driuen away.</p>
               <p>The Gouernor of <hi>Dixmuyde</hi> chéefe of Two Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men hath made his aſſault vpon the <hi>Porquepycke</hi> then in vaine, and beaten away.</p>
               <p>One Captaine with Fiue Hundred men thinking to force the Weſt Rauelin, was alſo beaten from thence.</p>
               <p>Another Captaine with Fiue Hundred men mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to effect ſome thing vppon the <hi>South Carre,</hi> was valiantly reſiſted.</p>
               <p>The Sargeant Maior with a Thouſand men mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ouer-runne the <hi>Weſt Carre</hi> was alſo manful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beaten away.</p>
               <p>This is as much as concerneth the Aſſault.</p>
               <p>The other day being the Eight of Ianuarie <hi>1602.</hi> (according to their ſtile) there was diuers Priſoners brought to diuers places for further examination: It
<pb facs="tcp:13946:3"/>is held that in the aſſaults and in the retreat, from the Towne more then a Thouſand were ſlaine without thoſe which were hurt. In the Euening of this eight day there fledde ouer one of the Enemies men, who reporteth that the Arch-duke in the morning woulde come &amp; aſſault again, and that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Walons and Dutches ſhould aſſault by reaſon the Spanyards and Italians had aſſaulted, for the which our Souldiers within did greatly longe for that they had gotten good booties of ſignor Spanyards.</p>
               <p>On the Nineth of the ſame there was found one dead verie richly apparelled eſtéemed to be ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder, hee was booted and ſpurd, it was thought his horſe was ſhot, and drowned.</p>
               <p>The Tenth of the ſame our ſouldiers thinking that the Enemie would againe make an aſſault, they haue expected them with good deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hope of more ſpoile.</p>
               <p>The Towne is dayly much fortified, ſo that they doe not greatly feare the Enemie.</p>
               <p>On the Eleauenth of the ſame a Drumme was ſent from the Enemie for to know what priſoners they had of qualitie: alſo to haue a ſurceaſe of armes for Two or Thrée houres, for to fetch or burie their dead, but it was not graunted. In the afternoone of the ſame day, came many Shalopes and Ship-boats full of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours out of the Fléete into the Towne in the ſight of the Enemie, notwithſtanding that they ſhat verie fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly without doing any manifeſt harme more then that they ſhot Thrée men, and one ſhip in the ground, wherein were moſt Mariners, but all ſaued, (God bée praiſed.)</p>
               <p>The Twelueth of the ſame in the Morning about Nine of the clocke, our men haue yet founde one dead carcaſſe with veluet breches layde on with gould lace, and a gilt Rapier about him who was drowned, it is thought he was ſome Commander.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13946:4"/>
               <p>About this time haue our men brought in a Wallon ſouldiour from the Eaſt, who reporteth that they haue loſt about Twelue hundred men.</p>
               <p>The Enemie hath again ſent a Drum for to enquire after ſome great Perſonages priſoners of qualitie: whereupon vuto him was anſweared that hee ſhould make ſpecification of the names what priſoners hee ſought, the ſpeech is that the Earle of <hi>Tributio</hi> or <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ùúlſie</hi> of <hi>Milayne</hi> cozen to the Duke of <hi>Mantua, Maiſtro del Campo</hi> ſhould be ſlaine.</p>
               <p>They doe continue yet verie ſtrong in the fortiſying and ſtrengthning of the Towne: God preſerue all the Gouernours, Captaines, Officers and Souldiours, with all others of the Towne, and take them to his protection.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Names of thoſe which were ſlaine.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Symon Antony Mr. del Campo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Don Aluares Schuares Crucia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, <hi>or of the order of St. Iames croſse.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Earle of Imbeeke Italian <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed to be rich, his reuenews of</hi> 300 <hi>Pistolets a day.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Sargeant maior Generall <hi>that was pledge within Oastend the</hi> 25 <hi>of December last paſt.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13946:4"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Durago Mr. del Campo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Lieutenant <hi>of the Gouernour of Antwarpe.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the dead is alſo found a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man perſon.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>After this a Drum of the Enemy hath declared that there were Twelue Hundreth men flaine and one Thouſand hurt, without thoſe which are caried away with waggons, and which were drowned, and driuen away in Sea by the water of the Sluce.</p>
               <p>Thoſe which aſſaulted in the old Towne had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or males with them, wherein they had prouided themſelues of victuals for ij. or iij. dayes, they had alſo Shouels, Pickaxes, Hatchets, Spades, and Ladders, and other Inſtruments which they all left behinde, to that end brought thether, according to the declaration of an <hi>Alfero</hi> or enſigne bearer, for to make place of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence for them in the old Towne.</p>
               <p>The péeces of Ordinance ſtanding in the <hi>Porque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyke</hi> and <hi>Faulſe breye</hi> were caſt downe in the aſſault, to the end if the Enemie had gotten the ſayde places, or any of them, he cold not haue vſed the ſame againſt the Towne.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
